Inventory of the Mills E. Godwin Jr. Papers 1947-1989
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin Jr., 1947-1978. (Box-folder 1-15:1-325)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1957. (Box-folder 1:16-18)
    Correspondence and articles regarding school integration; Godwin challenging Republican candidate for governor relating to Public Assignment Plan and opposition thereto; Godwin's appearance before State Highway Commission advocating north-south route for Chesapeake Bay Bridge and Tunnel, and letters which followed as result of his stand; Godwin's letter of congratulations to Governor-elect Almond; his stated desire for appointment of Senate Finance Committee; Report on Fluoridation of Public Water supplies.
    - General Correspondence, January-April 1957. (Box-folder 1:16)
    - General Correspondence, May-August 1957. (Box-folder 1:17)
    - General Correspondence, September-December 1957. (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1958. (Box-folder 1:19-21)
    Correspondence reveals Godwin's appointment as a member of Commission on Constitutional Government, with copy of Chapter 223 creating said Commission included (legislation of which he was a patron); assignment to the Senate Finance Committee; correspondence regarding the Norfolk school closings, news clippings on same; synopsis of four bills passed relating to segregation of public schools; letters favoring Godwin's views on school situation; letters regarding his speech made November 3 on the school issue; church and civic involvement; speaking engagements; Godwin's hospitalization in February-March; his trip to Nassau; trip to New York; extension requested for filing tax return; correspondence regarding Judge Lawrence W. I'Anson's ceremony.
    - General Correspondence, January-April 1958. (Box-folder 1:19)
    - General Correspondence, May-September 1958. (Box-folder 1:20)
    - General Correspondence, October-December 1958. (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1958-1959. (Box-folder 1:22)
    Correspondence covering matters relating to the Commission on Constitutional Government, its organizational set-up, Executive Committee's instructions, etc; an editorial entitled "Campaign for the Constitution", and correspondence with James J. Kilpatrick of the Richmond News Leader.
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1959. (Box-folder 2:23-25)
    Many legislative matters such as the school integration issue, the sales tax issue, resolution calling for special session of Legislature with the telegrams of support; proposed bill to control outdoor advertising supported by many garden clubs throughout the State; invitations to Godwin for speaking engagements from church groups, civic groups and other functions; letter from Congressman Robertson expressing relief that no one else filed for the State Senate seat held by Senator Godwin; Godwin's correspondence transmitting his qualification fee for candidacy for Senate seat, subsequently followed by the Clerk of Court of Southampton County certifying Godwin elected as Senator for another term; news clipping regarding Godwin for governor.
    - General Correspondence, January-March 1959. (Box-folder 2:23)
    - General Correspondence, April-August 1959. (Box-folder 2:24)
    - General Correspondence, September-December 1959. (Box-folder 2:25)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1960. (Box-folder 2:26-29)
    Correspondence regarding the sales tax issue; a resolution regarding the removal of the additional 16Â¢ charge on gasoline; appreciation on passage of billboard control bill and Godwin's stand opposing the current sales tax measure; article on Governor Almond's verbal attack on Godwin and others instrumental in defeating current sales tax measure; speaking engagements; church and civic involvement; gift acknowledgments; letters of condolence; correspondence regarding Katherine Godwin's operation in late 1959; letter to Harry F. Byrd, Jr. regarding the political scene for 1961; Godwin chosen First Citizen of Suffolk and Nansemond County; communications from citizens throughout the Commonwealth for his candidacy for lieutenant-governor on Democratic ticket for 1961.
    - General Correspondence, January-March 1960. (Box-folder 2:26)
    - General Correspondence, April-June 1960. (Box-folder 2:27)
    - General Correspondence, July-September 1960. (Box-folder 2:28)
    - General Correspondence, October-December 1960. (Box-folder 2:29)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1961. (Box-folder 2:30-34)
    Correspondence and statements regarding the Democratic ticket "Harrison, Godwin and Button"; signed petitions and other requirements needed for candidacy; Godwin's views on education in a copy of the Virginia Journal on Education; statements on Education and Government, Virginia's Right to Work Act and school integration; campaign information on Booth's stand on issues, criticism of Byrd Machine; copy of a speech made by Harry F. Byrd, Sr. on Right to Work law; campaign statement on "Why You Should Vote For Harrison, Godwin and Button" - a clear definition between conservatism and liberalism; sample ballot; Harrison's speech for ticket; Godwin's schedule during campaign (partial); letters on Primary race; news article regarding Godwin campaign; letters on the November campaign; speaking engagements and strategy; congratulatory messages following election, one of which was sent by Governor Almond.
    - General Correspondence, January-March 1961. (Box-folder 2:30)
    - General Correspondence, April-July 1961. (Box-folder 2:31)
    - General Correspondence, August 1961. (Box-folder 2:32)
    - General Correspondence, September-October 1961. (Box-folder 2:33)
    - General Correspondence, November-December 1961. (Box-folder 2:34)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1962. (Box-folder 2:35-37)
    Godwin's inauguration as lieutenant-governor (Folder 35); correspondence on the election; invitations to the inauguration and legislative matters; letters to Godwin concerning his residing over the Senate during the session; church and civic involvement; speaking engagements; correspondence on the theft of Mrs. Godwin's brooch while in Roanoke, Virginia.
    - General Correspondence, January-February 1962. (Box-folder 2:35)
    - General Correspondence, March 1962. (Box-folder 2:36)
    - General Correspondence, April 1962. (Box-folder 2:37)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1963. (Box-folder 2:38)
    News clippings; a trip to the Mediterranean (Virginia Ports sales talk); correspondence and speech to representatives of the Sigma Delta Chi at Williamsburg; letter from Godwin to Senator Walker congratulating him on successful Primary race; letter from George Kostel regarding his recent campaign.
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1964. (Box-folder 2:39-44)
    Legislative correspondence regarding the Library Amendment; possible sales tax next year; appointment of pages; legislators to various committees; Godwin's letters to all senators, stenographers and pages expressing his appreciation for their assistance during the session; invitations; church and civic involvements; speaking engagements and condolences; article from The Dickensonian regarding Godwin and another regarding his possible candidacy for governor; letters from Virginians offering support to Godwin if candidate for governor.
    - General Correspondence, 1-23 January 1964. (Box-folder 2:39)
    - General Correspondence, 24-31 January 1964. (Box-folder 2:40)
    - General Correspondence, 1-13 February 1964. (Box-folder 2:41)
    - General Correspondence, 14-29 February 1964. (Box-folder 2:42)
    - General Correspondence, March-July 1964. (Box-folder 2:43)
    - General Correspondence, August-December 1964. (Box-folder 2:44)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1965. (Box-folder 3-5:45-100)
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., January-September 1965. (Box-folder 3:45-70)
      Correspondence covers the period of Godwin's campaign for the Democratic Primary for governor; the possible closing of Public Health Services Hospital in Norfolk; matters relating to Washington and old Dominion Railway; campaign matters, such as support letters, news clippings; correspondence regarding his announcement of candidacy; statement released to the press announcing his candidacy; letters to and replies from legislators and others seeking support; letters acknowledging unsolicited contributions; letters seeking support from Virginia Congressional Delegation; letters pledging support of candidacy, financial contributions received and acknowledged; letter to Harry Byrd, Jr. thanking him for support; letters regarding lieutenant-governor spot and his own personal political philosophy; acknowledgments of Christmas gifts.
      - General Correspondence, 1-11 January 1965. (Box-folder 3:45)
      - General Correspondence, 12-13 January 1965. (Box-folder 3:46)
      - General Correspondence, 14-15 January 1965. (Box-folder 3:47)
      - General Correspondence, 16-19 January 1965. (Box-folder 3:48)
      - General Correspondence, 20-21 January 1965. (Box-folder 3:49)
      - General Correspondence, 22-25 January 1965. (Box-folder 3:50)
      - General Correspondence, 26-31 January 1965. (Box-folder 3:51)
      - General Correspondence, 1-10 February 1965. (Box-folder 3:52)
      - General Correspondence, 11-16 February 1965. (Box-folder 3:53)
      - General Correspondence, 17-28 February 1965. (Box-folder 3:54)
      - General Correspondence, 1-8 March 1965. (Box-folder 3:55)
      - General Correspondence, 9-15 March 1965. (Box-folder 3:56)
      - General Correspondence, 16-31 March 1965. (Box-folder 3:57)
      - General Correspondence, April 1965. (Box-folder 3:58)
      - General Correspondence, May 1965. (Box-folder 3:59)
      - General Correspondence, June 1965. (Box-folder 3:60)
      - General Correspondence, July 1965. (Box-folder 3:61)
      - General Correspondence, 1-22 August 1965. (Box-folder 3:62)
      - General Correspondence, 23-31 August 1965. (Box-folder 3:63)
      - General Correspondence, 1-8 September 1965. (Box-folder 3:64)
      - General Correspondence, 9-13 September 1965. (Box-folder 3:65)
      - General Correspondence, 14-15 September 1965. (Box-folder 3:66)
      - General Correspondence, 16-20 September 1965. (Box-folder 3:67)
      - General Correspondence, 21-23 September 1965. (Box-folder 3:68)
      - General Correspondence, 24-27 September 1965. (Box-folder 3:69)
      - General Correspondence, 28-30 September 1965. (Box-folder 3:70)
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., October 1965. (Box-folder 4:71-79)
      News articles; releases; campaign correspondence; speaking engagements; letters of appreciation to individuals; letters regarding contributions.
      - General Correspondence, 1-5 October 1965. (Box-folder 4:71)
      - General Correspondence, 6-10 October 1965. (Box-folder 4:72)
      - General Correspondence, 11-12 October 1965. (Box-folder 4:73)
      - General Correspondence, 13-14 October 1965. (Box-folder 4:74)
      - General Correspondence, 15-19 October 1965. (Box-folder 4:75)
      - General Correspondence, 20-23 October 1965. (Box-folder 4:76)
      - General Correspondence, 24-26 October 1965. (Box-folder 4:77)
      - General Correspondence, 27-29 October 1965. (Box-folder 4:78)
      - General Correspondence, 30-31 October 1965. (Box-folder 4:79)
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., November-December 1965. (Box-folder 4:80-97)
      Congratulatory letters; letters of appreciation to campaign workers; invitations to inaugural ceremonies; correspondence regarding temporary office space and secretary for new governor; new administration; legislative assignments; state public school formula; correspondence from A. Linwood Holton and response; letter from Governor Albertis Harrison and Chief Justice Eggleston; correspondence regarding speech by governor-elect at Tidewater Rehabilitation Institute; Godwin's brief hospitalization; correspondence with Waldo Miles regarding gift of mink stole for Mrs. Miles.
      - General Correspondence, 1-2 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:80)
      - General Correspondence, 3 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:81)
      - General Correspondence, 3 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:82)
      - General Correspondence, 4 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:83)
      - General Correspondence, 5 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:84)
      - General Correspondence, 6-7 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:85)
      - General Correspondence, 8 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:86)
      - General Correspondence, 9 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:87)
      - General Correspondence, 10-11 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:88)
      - General Correspondence, 12 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:89)
      - General Correspondence, 13-15 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:90)
      - General Correspondence, 16-17 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:91)
      - General Correspondence, 18-19 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:92)
      - General Correspondence, 20-22 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:93)
      - General Correspondence, 23 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:94)
      - General Correspondence, 24-30 November 1965. (Box-folder 4:95)
      - General Correspondence, 1-10 December 1965. (Box-folder 4:96)
      - General Correspondence, 11-31 December 1965. (Box-folder 4:97)
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1965-1966. (Box-folder 5:98-100)
      Invitations; programs, copies of prayer by the Reverend Dwight W. Moore.
      - Campaign Material, 1965. (Box-folder 5:98)
      - Campaign Material, 1965. (Box-folder 5:99)
      - inauguration Material, January 1966. (Box-folder 5:100)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1966. (Box-folder 5:101-112)
    Church activities; letters regarding hospital visit, insurance; honorary degree awarded by the college of William and Mary; news articles regarding governor's new administration; correspondence regarding keynote of governor's Conference on Education.
    - General Correspondence, January 1966. (Box-folder 5:101)
    - Congratulatory Message, 1-16 January 1966. (Box-folder 5:102)
    - Congratulatory Message, 17-19 January 1966. (Box-folder 5:103)
    - Congratulatory Message, 20-31 January 1966. (Box-folder 5:104)
    - General Correspondence, February 1966. (Box-folder 5:105)
    - General Correspondence, March 1966. (Box-folder 5:106)
    - General Correspondence, April-June 1966. (Box-folder 5:107)
    - General Correspondence, July-September 1966. (Box-folder 5:108)
    - General Correspondence, October-December 1966. (Box-folder 5:109)
    - Gifts to the Governor, January-June 1966. (Box-folder 5:110)
    - Gifts to the Governor, July-December 1966. (Box-folder 5:111)
    - Christmas Card List, December 1966. (Box-folder 5:112)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1967. (Box-folder 5:113-121)
    Editorial in Washington Post regarding first Administration and correspondence regarding same; letters and articles regarding European Trade Mission; news articles; letter to Governor Lurleen Wallace, governor of Alabama; printed copy of address given by Godwin at Jefferson-Jackson Day dinner and correspondence regarding same.
    - General Correspondence, January 1967. (Box-folder 5:113)
    - General Correspondence, February 1967. (Box-folder 5:114)
    - General Correspondence, March 1967. (Box-folder 5:115)
    - General Correspondence, April-May 1967. (Box-folder 5:116)
    - General Correspondence, June-August 1967. (Box-folder 5:117)
    - General Correspondence, September-October 1967. (Box-folder 5:118)
    - General Correspondence, November-December 1967. (Box-folder 5:119)
    - Gifts to the Governor, January-June 1967. (Box-folder 5:120)
    - Gifts to the Governor, July-December 1967. (Box-folder 5:121)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1968. (Box-folder 6:122-129)
    Editorials in Rural Virginia and Richmond Times-Dispatch on governor's administration; correspondence on administration; article in Virginia Poultryman on bond issue.
    - General Correspondence, January-February 1968. (Box-folder 6:122)
    - General Correspondence, March-May 1968. (Box-folder 6:123)
    - General Correspondence, June-July 1968. (Box-folder 6:124)
    - General Correspondence, August-September 1968. (Box-folder 6:125)
    - General Correspondence, October-December 1968. (Box-folder 6:126)
    - Gifts to the Governor, January-August 1968. (Box-folder 6:127)
    - Gifts to the Governor, September-December 1968. (Box-folder 6:128)
    - Research Paper, 1968. (Box-folder 6:129)
      Research Paper; Changing Posture of the Democratic Party in Virginia As Seen in its Leadership - Mills Edwin Godwin, Jr., Exemplar of the Change, by Judith Rountree Elliott.
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1969 (Box-folder 6:130-138)
    Article, The Godwin Years appearing in Commonwealth Magazine and Virginia's European headquarters for industrial development inaugurated by Godwin.
    - General Correspondence, January-February 1969. (Box-folder 6:130)
    - General Correspondence, March-May 1969. (Box-folder 6:131)
    - General Correspondence, June-July 1969. (Box-folder 6:132)
    - Article, The Godwin Years appearing in Commonwealth Magazine, July 1969. (Box-folder 6:133)
    - General Correspondence, August-October 1969. (Box-folder 6:134)
    - General Correspondence, November 1969. (Box-folder 6:135)
    - General Correspondence, December 1969. (Box-folder 6:136)
    - Gifts to the Governor, January-August 1969. (Box-folder 6:137)
    - Gifts to the Governor, September-December 1969. (Box-folder 6:138)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1970. (Box-folder 7:139-154)
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., January 1970. (Box-folder 7:139-142)
      Letters on pardon of youth involved in drug charge; letters of appreciation to Mansion staff; notes and other matters relating to No Higher Honor; letters to and from state legislators.
      - General Correspondence, 1-14 January 1970. (Box-folder 7:139)
      - General Correspondence, January 15-31 1970. (Box-folder 7:140)
      - Complimentary letters on Administration, 1-12 January 1970. (Box-folder 7:141)
      - Complimentary letters on Administration, 13-31 January 1970. (Box-folder 7:142)
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., February 1970. (Box-folder 7:143-144)
      Correspondence regarding membership on bank boards; recognitions and invitations for speaking engagements.
      - General Correspondence, 1-16 February 1970. (Box-folder 7:143)
      - General Correspondence, 14-28 February 1970. (Box-folder 7:144)
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., March 1970. (Box-folder 7:145)
      Correspondence regarding naming of school in Prince William County for Godwin; speaking engagements: dedication of Henry Clay Hofheimer Library; announcement by Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., to run as Independent; correspondence with Mr. Carl Andrews.
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., April 1970. (Box-folder 7:146)
      Recognitions; letters regarding membership on Board of Trustees of Virginia Foundation for Independent Colleges; letters regarding Administration; speaking engagements; Congressman Watkins M. Abbitt's announced retirement.
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., May 1970. (Box-folder 7:147)
      Congratulatory messages; Fox portrait of Godwin.
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., June 1970. (Box-folder 7:148)
      Letters on appointment to Boards; further correspondence relating to No Higher Honor; honorary degree from Washington & Lee University; speaking engagements.
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., July-August 1970. (Box-folder 7:149)
      Honorary membership in Phi Theta Kappa at Thomas Nelson Community College; speaking engagements; letters regarding former Governor Thomas B. Stanley's death and Senatorial campaign of Harry F. Byrd, Jr.
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., September-October 1970. (Box-folder 7:150)
      Lieutenant-governor Sargent Reynolds' illness; ceremonies for Paul D. Camp Community College, Lord Fairfax Community College, and Virginia Highlands Community College.
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., November 1970. (Box-folder 7:151)
      Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr.'s victory; Constitutional amendments approved by voters; letters of appreciation for copy of book of speeches - first administration.
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., December 1970. (Box-folder 7:152)
      Letters regarding possible appointment to Supreme Court and denial; article in Virginia Observer regarding President Nixon asking Godwin for aid for oil refinery at Hampton Roads; letters on future of Democratic Party in Virginia.
    - U. S. Senate campaign - Harry F. Byrd, Jr., July-October 1970. (Box-folder 7:153)
    - U. S. Senate campaign - Harry F. Byrd, Jr., November-December 1970. (Box-folder 7:154)
  - Virginians for the Constitution, 1970-1971. (Box-folder 7:155)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1971. (Box-folder 7-8:156-169)
    General Correspondence.
    - General Correspondence, January 1971. (Box-folder 7:156)
    - General Correspondence, February 1971. (Box-folder 7:157)
    - General Correspondence, 1-16 March 1971. (Box-folder 7:158)
    - General Correspondence, 17-31 March 1971. (Box-folder 7:159)
    - General Correspondence, April 1971. (Box-folder 8:160)
    - General Correspondence, May 1971. (Box-folder 8:161)
    - General Correspondence, June 1971. (Box-folder 8:162)
    - General Correspondence, July 1971. (Box-folder 8:163)
    - General Correspondence, August 1971. (Box-folder 8:164)
    - General Correspondence, 1-14 September 1971. (Box-folder 8:165)
    - General Correspondence, 15-30 September 1971. (Box-folder 8:166)
    - General Correspondence, October 1971. (Box-folder 8:167)
    - General Correspondence, November 1971. (Box-folder 8:168)
    - General Correspondence, December 1971. (Box-folder 8:169)
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., September 1971 - January 1972. (Box-folder 8:170)
    Campaign for lieutenant-governor, George Kostel
  - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., 1972. (Box-folder 8-9:171-188)
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., January-June 1972. (Box-folder 8:171-177)
      Correspondence, printed material and other items related to Godwin's nomination as the Republican candidate for governor; the presidential election; news articles entitled "Godwin Draft" and "The Push for Godwin"; speaking engagements; comments made by Godwin on busing of school children; statement on White House visit; plans for organizing "Order of White Jackets" Carl Andrews; article and letters regarding dedication of Godwin Hall at Madison College; correspondence and other matters regarding Constitutional Amendment ending tenure for federal judges; letter from Richard D. Obenshain inviting Godwin to run on Republican ticket.
      - General Correspondence, January 1972. (Box-folder 9:171)
      - General Correspondence, February 1972. (Box-folder 9:172)
      - General Correspondence, March 1972. (Box-folder 9:173)
      - General Correspondence, April 1972. (Box-folder 9:174)
      - General Correspondence, May 1972. (Box-folder 9:175)
      - General Correspondence, 1-18 June 1972. (Box-folder 9:176)
      - General Correspondence, 19-30 June 1972. (Box-folder 9:177)
    - Correspondence of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., July-December 1972. (Box-folder 9:178-188)
      - General Correspondence, 1-12 July 1972. (Box-folder 9:178)
      - General Correspondence, 13-31 July 1972. (Box-folder 9:179)
      - General Correspondence, 1-15 August 1972. (Box-folder 9:180)
      - General Correspondence, August 16-31 1972. (Box-folder 9:181)
      - General Correspondence, September 1972. (Box-folder 9:182)